I want you to take a trip with me.
أريد أن آخذكم معي في رحلة.
Picture yourself driving
تخيلوا أنفسكم تقودون سيارتكم
down a small road in Africa,
على طريق صغير في أفريقيا،
and as you drive along, you look off to the side,
و بينما أنتم سائرون، تنظرون جانبا
and this is what you see:
و هذا هو ما ترونه.
you see a field of graves.
ترون ساحةً من القبور.
And you stop, and you get out of your car and you take a picture.
فتتوقفون، و تهبطون من السيارة لتلتقطوا صورة.
And you go into the town,
ثم تدخلون إلى المدينة،
and you inquire, "What's going on here?"
و تسألون، "ما الذي يجري هنا؟"
and people are initially reluctant to tell you.
و تجد الناس مترددين في إخبارك
And then someone says,
ثم يقول أحدهم،
"These are the recent AIDS deaths in our community."
"تلك وفيات حديثة من مرض الأيدز في مجتمعنا."
HIV isn't like other medical conditions;
مرض الأيدز ليس كالحالات المرضية الآخرى،
it's stigmatizing.
إنه يعد وصمة عار.
People are reluctant to talk about it --
يكره الناس الحديث عنه.
there's a fear associated with it.
هناك خوف و قلق مرتبط به.
And I'm going to talk about HIV today,
و اليوم سأتحدث عن مرض نقص المناعة المكتسبة.
about the deaths,
و عن الوفيات،
about the stigma.
و عن العار.
It's a medical story, but more than that, it's a social story.
إنها قصة طبية، و لكن الأهم من ذلك أنها قصة إجتماعية.
This map depicts the global distribution of HIV.
تلك الخريطة توضح توزيع إنتشار الHIV في العالم.
And as you can see,
و كما ترون،
Africa has a disproportionate share of the infection.
حصة أفريقيا من العدوى غير متناسبة.
There are 33 million people
هناك 33 مليون شخص
living with HIV in the world today.
حاملا للفيروس في العالم اليوم.
Of these, two-thirds, 22 million
ثلثي هؤلاء، 22 مليون،
are living in sub-Saharan Africa.
يقطنون في إفريقيا جنوب الصحراء الكبرى.
There are 1.4 million pregnant women
هناك 1.4 مليون إمرأة حامل
in low- and middle-income countries living with HIV
في دول منخفضة و متوسطة الدخل ، تعيش حاملةً المرض،
and of these, 90 percent
و من هؤلاء، 90 بالمائة
are in sub-Saharan Africa.
يعشن في إفريقيا جنوب الصحراء.
We talk about things in relative terms.
نحن نتحدث عن الأشياء بمنظور النسبية.
And I'm going to talk about annual pregnancies
و سأتحدث الآن عن النسبة السنوية للأمهات و
and HIV-positive mothers.
الحوامل الحاملات للHIV.
The United States -- a large country --
الولايات المتحدة، وهي دولة كبيرة،
each year, 7,000 mothers with HIV
سنوياً،تجد7000 أم حاملة للHIV
who give birth to a child.
يلدن أطفالاً.
But you go to Rwanda -- a very small country --
و لكن إذا ذهبت إلى رواندا --وهي دولة صغيرة جداً--
8,000 mothers with HIV who are pregnant.
تجد 8000 أم حامل، مصابة بالHIV.
And then you go to Baragwanath Hospital,
ثم نذهب إلى مستشفى باراجوانث،
outside of Johannesburg in South Africa,
خارج جوهانسبرج في جنوب إفريقيا،
and 8,000 HIV-positive pregnant women
و تجد 8000 أم حامل،مصابة بالHIV
giving birth --
و اللاتي يلدن--
a hospital the same as a country.
تساوت مستشفى مع دولة.
And to realize that this is just the tip of an iceberg
و لتدرك أن ما ذلك إلا قمة الجبل الجليدي،
that when you compare
لأنه عندما نقارن
everything here to South Africa, it just pales,
كل تلك البيانات بجنوب إفريقيا، فإنها باهتة،
because in South Africa,
لأنه في جنوب إفريقيا
each year 300,000 mothers with HIV
هناك 300.000 أم حاملة للHIV سنويا
give birth to children.
ينجبن أطفالاً!
So we talk about PMTCT,
إذن فنحن نتحدث عن PMTCT ،
and we refer to PMTCT, prevention of mother to child transmission.
قاصداً، الوقاية ضد إنتقال العدوى من الأم إلى الطفل.
I think there's an assumption amongst most people in the public
أعتقد أنه هناك إفتراض بين معظم عامة الناس أنه
that if a mother is HIV-positive,
لو أن الأم حاملة لفيروس الHIV،
she's going to infect her child.
فإنها ستعدى طفلها.
The reality is really, very different.
وواقع الأمور مختلف تماما.
In resource-rich countries,
في دول غنية بالموارد،
with all the tests and treatment we currently have,
و مع وجود جميع الإختبارات و سبل العلاج ،
less than two percent of babies are born HIV-positive --
أقل من 2 % من الأطفال يولدون حاملين للفيروس.
98 percent of babies are born HIV-negative.
و 98 بالمائة من الأطفال نتيجتهم سلبية.
And yet, the reality in resource-poor countries,
و مع ذلك فالواقع في الدول فقيرة الموارد،
in the absence of tests and treatment,
مع غياب الفحوصات و العلاج،
40 percent -- 40 percent of children are infected --
40 بالمائة، 40 بالمائة من الأطفال مصابين--
40 percent versus two percent --
40 بالمائة مقابل 2 بالمائة --
an enormous difference.
فارق شاسع.
So these programs --
إذاً فتلك البرامج--
and I'm going to refer to PMTCT though my talk --
وأنا أعني برامج PMTCT خلال حديثي --
these prevention programs,
برامج الوقاية تلك،
simply, they're the tests and the drugs that we give to mothers
ببساطة، هي عبارة عن الفحوصات و الأدوية التي نعطيها إلى الأمهات
to prevent them from infecting their babies,
لمنع إنتقال العدوى منهن إلى أطفالهن،
and also the medicines we give to mothers
وهي أيضاً الأدوية التي نعطيها للأمهات
to keep them healthy and alive to raise their children.
للحفاظ على حياتهن و بقائهن أصحاء لتربية ابنائهن.
So it's the test a mother gets when she comes in.
إذن فهي الإختبارات التي نجريها على الأم عند حضورها.
It's the drugs she receives
هي الأدوية التي تتلقاها
to protect the baby that's inside the uterus and during delivery.
لحماية جنينها داخل الرحم و اثناء الولادة.
It's the guidance she gets around infant feeding
وهي التوجيه التي تتلقاه عن إطعام الرضّع
and safer sex.
و عن الجماع الآمن.
It's an entire package of services,
هي كل تلك الخدمات مجتمعة،
and it works.
وهي فعّالة.
So in the United States,
إذاً في الولايات المتحدة،
since the advent of treatment in the middle of the 1990s,
منذ إكتشاف العلاج في منتصف التسعينيات،
there's been an 80-percent decline
كان هناك إنخفاض بنسبة 80 بالمائة
in the number of HIV-infected children.
في عدد الأطفال المصابين بالHIV.
Less than 100 babies are born with HIV
أقل من 100 طفل يولدون حاملين الHIV
each year in the United States
سنوياً في الولايات المتحدة،
and yet, still,
و مع ذلك، لا زال
over 400,000 children
هناك أكثر من 400.000 طفل
are born every year in the world today with HIV.
يولدون حاملين الHIV سنويا في العالم.
What does that mean?
مالذي يعنيه ذلك؟
It means 1,100 children infected each day --
هذا يعني أنه يولد يوميا 1.100 طفل مصاب --
1,100 children each day, infected with HIV.
1.100 طفل كل يوم، مصابين بالHIV.
And where do they come from?
و من أين يأتي هؤلاء؟
Well, less than one comes from the United States.
حسناً، أقل من واحد في الولايات المتحدة.
One, on average, comes from Europe.
بمعدل واحد في أوروبا.
100 come from Asia and the Pacific.
100 من أسيا و دول المحيط الهادئ.
And each day,
و كل يوم،
a thousand babies -- a thousand babies
ألف طفل، ألف طفل!
are born each day with HIV in Africa.
يولدون يومياً حاملين الHIV في افريقيا.
So again, I look at the globe here
إذاً مرة أخرى ننظر إلى العالم هنا
and the disproportionate share of HIV in Africa.
و نصيب افريقيا الغير متكافئ من الHIV.
And let's look at another map.
و دعونا نلقي نظرة على خريطة أخرى.
And here, again, we see
و هنا، مجدداً، نلاحظ
Africa has a disproportionate share of the numbers of doctors.
أن نصيب إفريقيا غير متكافئ في عدد الأطباء.
That thin sliver you see here, that's Africa.
تلك الشريحة الرفيعة التي ترونها هنا، هي إفريقيا.
And it's the same with nurses.
و نفس الشئ مع عدد الممرضات.
The truth is sub-Saharan Africa
الحقيقة هي أن افريقيا جنوب الصحراء
has 24 percent
تحوي 24 بالمائة
of the global disease burden
من عبء المرض في العالم،
and yet only three percent of the world's health care workers.
و في الوقت ذاته، تحوى فقط 3 بالمائة من عاملي الرعاية الصحية في العالم.
That means doctors and nurses
مما يعني أن الأطباء و الممرضات
simply don't have the time to take care of patients.
الموجودين لن يتوافر لهم الوقت لرعاية المرضى.
A nurse in a busy clinic
الممرضة في عيادة ذات ضغط
will see 50 to 100 patients in a day,
نرى فيها من 50 إلى 100 مريض يومياً،
which leaves her just minutes per patient --
يترك لها فقط بضع دقائق لتقضيها مع كل مريض --
minutes per patient.
دقائق لكل مريض.
And so when we look at these PMTCT programs, what does it mean?
و عندما ننظر إلى برامج PMTCT تلك، ما الذي تمثله؟
Well, back in 2001,
حسناً، في عام 2001،
when there was just a simple test
عندما كان يجرى إختبار واحد بسيط
and a single dose of a drug,
و جرعة وحيدة من الدواء،
a nurse, in the course of her few minutes with a patient,
كان على الممرضة، خلال الدقائق القليلة التي تقضيها مع المريض،
would have to counsel for the HIV test, perform the HIV test,
أن تنصح بإختبار الHIV، و تقوم بإجراءه،
explain the results, dispense a single dose of the drug, Nevirapine,
و تشرح النتائج، و تعطي جرعة الدواء وهو نيفيرابين،
explain how to take it, discuss infant feeding options, reinforce infant feeding,
و تشرح كيفية تناوله، تناقش خيارات إطعام الرضع، و تؤكد على ضرورته،
and test the baby -- in minutes.
و تقوم بإختبار الرضيع، في بضع دقائق.
Well, fortunately since 2001,
حسنا، من حسن الحظ منذ 2001،
we've got new treatments, new tests,
توفرت لدينا المزيد من طرق العلاج و الإختبارات،
and we're far more successful,
و إزدادت نسبة النجاح كثيراً،
but we don't have any more nurses.
و لكن نسبة الممرضات ما زالت كما هي.
And so these are the tests
و تلك هي الإختبارات التي
a nurse now has to do
يجب ان تجريها الممرضة الآن
in those same few minutes.
في تلك الدقائق القليلة نفسها.
It's not possible --
وهذا ليس بممكن.
it doesn't work.
لا يفلح مطلقاً.
And so we need to find
إذاً يجب علينا أن نجد
better ways of providing care.
طرقاً أفضل لتقديم الرعاية.
This is a picture of a maternal health clinic in Africa --
تلك صورة عيادة لرعاية الأمومة في إفريقيا --
mothers coming, pregnant and with their babies.
تأتي الأمهات حوامل و مع اطفالهن.
These women are here for care,
اولئك السيدات أتوا هنا للحصول على الرعاية،
but we know that just doing a test,
و نحن نعلم أن مجرد إجراء إختبار
just giving someone a drug,
و مجرد إعطاء إحداهن عقاراً،
it's not enough.
ليس كافياً بالمرة.
Meds don't equal medical care.
الأدوية لا تساوي الرعاية الطبية.
Doctors and nurses, frankly,
بصراحة، ليس لدى الأطباء والممرضات
don't have the time or skills
الوقت ولا المهارات اللازمين
to tell people what to do in ways they understand.
لإخبار المرضى المطلوب منهم فعله بأسلوب مفهوم لهم.
I'm a doctor -- I tell people things to do,
انا طبيب. و انا أخبر المرضى ما يجب فعله،
and I expect them to follow my guidance --
و أتوقع منهم أن يتبعوا نصائحي --
because I'm a doctor; I went to Harvard --
و ذلك لأنني طبيب و تخرجت من جامعة هارفارد --
but the reality is,
و لكن الواقع هو
if I tell a patient, "You should have safer sex.
إذا اخبرت المريض، "يجب عليك ممارسة الجنس الآمن.
You should always use a condom,"
عليك بإستخدام الواقي الذكري دائماً،"
and yet, in her relationship, she's not empowered --
في الوقت ذاته الذي ليس لها رأي أو صوت في علاقتها --
what's going to happen?
ما الذي سيحدث؟
If I tell her to take her medicines every day
إذا نصحتها بأخذ أدويتها يومياً بإنتظام،
and yet, no one in the household knows about her illness, so
في الوقت الذي لا يعلم أحد من أهل منزلها بأمر مرضها، لذا
it's just not going to work.
لن تفعل ذلك.
And so we need to do more,
إذاً فنحن في حاجة إلى فعل المزيد
we need to do it differently,
بطريقة مختلفة،
we need to do it in ways that are affordable
بإستخدام طرق تكلفتها معقولة،
and accessible and can be taken to scale,
و متاحة و يمكن تطبيقها على نطاق واسع،
which means it can be done everywhere.
مما يعني أنه يمكن تطبيقها في أي مكان.
So, I want to tell you a story --
دعوني أخبركم قصة.
I want to take you on a little trip.
أريد أن آخذكم معي في رحلة.
Imagine yourself, if you can,
تخيل نفسك، لو ممكن،
you're a young woman in Africa, you're going to the hospital or clinic.
أنك إمرأة افريقية صغيرة السن، في طريقك إلى المستشفى أو العيادة.
You go in for a test
تجرين إختباراً،
and you find out that you're pregnant, and you're delighted.
و تكتشفين أنك حاملاً، فتغمركِ الفرحة.
And then they give you another test
ثم تجرين إختباراً آخر،
and they tell you you're HIV-positive, and you're devastated.
و يخبرونك أنك مصابة بالHIV ، فيغمرك الأسى.
And the nurse takes you into a room,
و تأخذك الممرضة إلى غرفة ما،
and she tells you about the tests
و تخبرك عن الإختبارات المطلوبة،
and HIV and the medicines you can take
و عن الإيدز و الأدوية اللازم تناولها
and how to take care of yourself and your baby,
و كيفية رعاية نفسك و طفلك،
and you hear none of it.
و لا يصلك أيٌ من هذا.
All you're hearing is, "I'm going to die,
كل ما تسمعينه هو، "أنني سأموت،
and my baby is going to die."
و أن طفلي سيموت."
And then you're out on the street, and you don't know where to go.
ثم تخرجين إلى الشارع، و لا تدرين إلى أين تلجئين.
And you don't know who you can talk to,
و لا تدرين إلى من تتحدثين،
because the truth is, HIV is so stigmatizing
لأن الواقع هو أن الإيدز هو وصمة عار لدرجة
that if you partner, your family, anyone in your home,
أنه لو علم بأمره زوجك، عائلتك أو أحد أفراد عائلتك،
you're likely to be thrown out
في الأغلب سيطردونك من المنزل
without any means of support.
بدون أي سبل إعاشة.
And this -- this is the face and story
وهذا هو الحال الحقيقي
of HIV in Africa today.
للHIV في أفريقيا اليوم.
But we're here to talk about possible solutions
و لكننا هنا لنتحدث عن حلول محتملة
and some good news.
و بعض الأخبار الجيدة.
And I want to change the story a little bit.
و أنا أرغب في تغيير القصة قليلاً.
Take the same mother, and the nurse, after she gives her her test,
تخيل نفس الأم، و بعد أن تجرى الممرضة الإختبار،
takes her to a room.
تأخذها إلى غرفة.
The door opens and there's a room full of mothers, mothers with babies,
يُفتح الباب لترى غرفة مليئة بالأمهات و أطفالهن،
and they're sitting, and they're talking, they're listening.
و هن جالسات يتحدثن و ينصتن فيما بينهن.
They're drinking tea, they're having sandwiches.
يشربن الشاي و يأكلن الشطائر.
And she goes inside, and woman comes up to her and says,
فتدخل ، وتأتي إحدى السيدات إليها قائلةً،
"Welcome to mothers2mothers.
"أهلاً بك في "من أم إلى أم."
Have a seat. You're safe here.
إجلسي، أنت في أمان هنا.
We're all HIV-positive.
نحن جميعنا مصابات بالHIV.
You're going to be okay. You're going to live.
و سوف تصبحين بخير. ستعيشين.
Your baby is going to be HIV-negative."
و طفلك لن يولد حاملا للHIV."
We view mothers
الأمهات من وجهة نظرنا
as a community's single greatest resource.
هن أعظم موارد المجتمع.
Mothers take care of the children, take care of the home.
فالأمهات يعتنين بالأطفال، و يهتممن بالبيت.
So often the men are gone.
الرجال في أغلب الوقت يكونون بالخارج.
They're working, or they're not part of the household.
إما يعملون، او قد لا يكونون جزئا من العائلة في الأساس.
Our organization, mothers2mothers,
منظمتنا، "من أم إلى أم"
enlists women with HIV
تقوم بتوظيف السيدات المصابات بالHIV
as care providers.
كمقدمات رعاية.
We bring mothers who have HIV,
نحن نُحضر الأمهات المصابات بالHIV،
who've been through these PMTCT programs
و اللاتي مررن ببرامج الوقاية PMTCT
in the very facilities,
في نفس المكان
to come back and work side by side with doctors and nurses
ليعدن، و ليعملن جنباً إلى جنب مع الأطباء و الممرضات
as part of the health care team.
كجزء من فريق الرعاية الصحية.
These mothers, we call them mentor mothers,
تلك الأمهات، نحن ندعوهم بالأمهات المرشدات،
are able to engage women
فلهن القدرة على مخاطبة النساء،
who, just like themselves, pregnant with babies,
اللاتي هن مثلهن يحملن أطفالاً،
have found out about being HIV-positive,
و أكتشفن أمر إصابتهن بالHIV،
who need support and education.
وهن في حاجة إلى المساندة و الإرشاد.
And they support them around the diagnosis
فيقمن بمساندتهن أثناء عملية التشخيص
and educate them about how to take their medicines,
و يرشدهن عن كيفية أخذ أدويتهن،
how to take care of themselves,
و كيف يهتممن بأنفسهن،
how to take care of their babies.
و كيفية رعاية أطفالهن.
Consider: if you needed surgery,
تأمل معي: لو أنت في حاجة إلى عملية جراحية
you would want the best possible technical surgeon, right?
ستود أن يؤديها أفضل جراح تقني موجود، صحيح؟
But if you wanted to understand
و لكن إذا أردت أن تعلم
what that surgery would do to your life,
تأثير تلك الجراحة على حياتك،
you'd like to engage someone,
فستريد أن تخاطب أحداً،
someone who's had the procedure.
قد خاض بنفس التجربة.
Patients are experts on their own experience,
المرضى هم الخبراء بشأن تجاربهم الخاصة،
and they can share that experience with others.
و يمكنهم مشاركة تجاربهم مع الآخرين.
This is the medical care that goes beyond just medicines.
تلك هي الرعاية الطبية التي تتخطى مجرد الأدوية.
So the mothers who work for us,
إذاً فالأمهات اللاتي يعملن لدينا،
they come from the communities in which they work.
قد نشأن من نفس المجتمعات التي يعملون فيها.
They're hired -- they're paid as professional members of the health care teams,
هم موظفات ، ويتلقون راتباً كأي عضو متخصص من فريق الرعاية الصحية،
just like doctors and nurses.
تماما كالأطباء و الممرضات.
And we open bank accounts for them
و نحن نقوم بفتح حسابات بنكية لهن،
and they're paid directly into the accounts,
و تدخل رواتبهم مباشرة في حساباتهم البنكية،
because their money's protected;
و بالتالي فما يكسبونه يصبح محمياً،
the men can't take it away from them.
و لا يستطيع الرجال أخذه منهن.
They go through two to three weeks
هن يمرون بأسبوعين إلى ثلاثة أسابيع
of rigorous curriculum-based education, training.
من التدريب و التعليم المنهجي الصارم.
Now, doctors and nurses -- they too get trained.
الآن، الأطباء و الممرضات أيضاً يتم تدريبهم
But so often, they only get trained once,
و لكن عادة يتلقون ذلك التدريب مرة واحدة فقط،
so they're not aware of new medicines,
فلا يكونون على دراية بالأدوية الحديثة،
new guidelines as they come out.
أو بالإرشادات التوجيهية الحديثة عند صدورها.
Our mentor mothers get trained every single year
أمهاتنا المرشدات يتم تدريبهم سنوياً
and retrained.
و يتكرر التدريب.
And so doctors and nurses --
فبالتالي الأطباء و الممرضات
they look up to them as experts.
ينظرون إليهم كخبيرات.
Imagine that: a woman, a former patient,
تخيل هذا: إمرأة، مريضة سابقة،
being able to educate her doctor for the first time
لها القدرة على تلقين طبيبها لأول مرة
and educate the other patients
و على إرشاد المرضى الآخرين
that she's taking care of.
الذين تقوم هي بالإعتناء بهم.
Our organization has three goals.
لمنظمتنا ثلاثة أهداف.
The first, to prevent mother-to-child transmission.
الأول، الوقاية من إنتقال المرض من الأم إلى الطفل.
The second: keep mothers healthy, keep mothers alive,
الثاني: أن نحافظ على صحة الأمهات و نبقيهن أحياء.
keep the children alive --
و نبقى أطفالهن أحياء.
no more orphans.
لا مزيد من الأيتام.
And the third, and maybe the most grand,
و الثالث، و ربما الأهم
is to find ways to empower women,
هو إيجاد طرقاً لتشجيع و تمكين النساء،
enable them to fight the stigma
أن نمكنهن من محاربة الخزي
and to live positive and productive lives with HIV.
و أن يعشن بإيجابية و إنتاجية برغم إصابتهن بالHIV.
So how do we do it?
إذاً كيف نفعل ذلك؟
Well, maybe the most important engagement
حسناً، ربكما أفضل طرق التخاطب
is the one-to-one,
هي فرد إلى فرد،
seeing patients one-to-one, educating them, supporting them,
أن نرى المرضى كلٍ على حدة، و نقوم بتعليمهم و مساندتهم
explaining how they can take care of themselves.
شارحين لهم كيفية الإعتناء بأنفسهم.
We go beyond that;
و نحن نتخطى ذلك.
we try to bring in the husbands, the partners.
نحاول أن نُشرك أزواجهن، أو شركاء علاقتهن.
In Africa, it's very, very hard to engage men.
في أفريقيا، من الصعب جداً جداً جذب إنتباه الرجال.
Men are not frequently part of pregnancy care.
فالرجال ليسوا عادة جزء من رعاية الحمل.
But in Rwanda, in one country,
و لكن في رواندا، في بلد واحد
they've got a policy
لديهم سياسة عمل
that a woman can't come for care
بأن لا تأتي سيدة لتلقي الرعاية
unless she brings the father of the baby with her --
بدون والد الجنين أو الطفل معها.
that's the rule.
هذه هي القاعدة.
And so the father and the mother, together,
فيأتي الأب و الأم معاً،
go through the counseling and the testing.
و يمرون بمراحل الإرشاد و الإختبار.
The father and the mother, together, they get the results.
الأب و الأم معاً يتلقون نتائج الفحوصات.
And this is so important in breaking through the stigma.
و هذا مهم جداً لتخطي حاجز الخوف من الخزي.
Disclosure is so central to prevention.
الإشهار و الكشف هو أساسي للوقاية.
How do you have safer sex, how do you use a condom regularly
فكيف يمكنك ممارسة جنس آمن، و كيف يمكنك الإستمرار في إستخدام الواقي الذكري
if there hasn't been disclosure?
إذا لم يكن هناك صراحة و علم مسبق؟
Disclosure is so important to treatment,
الإشهار مهم جداً للعلاج،
because again, people need the support of family members and friends
لأنه، مجدداً، المرضى في حاجة إلى مساندة أفراد العائلة و الأصدقاء
to take their medicines regularly.
حتى يتناولوا أدويتهم بإنتظام.
We also work in groups.
نحن أيضاً نعمل في مجموعات.
Now the groups, it's not like me lecturing,
الآن تلك المجموعات، ليست كمحاضرات
but what happens is women, they come together --
و لكن ما يحدث أن النساء يجتمعن --
under the support and guidance of our mentor mothers --
تحت رعاية و توجيه أمهاتنا المرشدات --
they come together, and they share their personal experiences.
يجتمعن، و يتشاركن تجاربهن الخاصة.
And it's through the sharing
و من خلال المشاركة
that people get tactics of how to take care of themselves,
يستطعن الخروج بخطط لكيفية الرعاية بإنفسهن،
how to disclose how to take medicines.
و كيفية الإفصاح عن الأمر، و كيفية تناول الأدوية.
And then there's the community outreach,
ثم هناك التوعية في المجتمعات،
engaging women in their communities.
مخاطبة النساء داخل مجتمعاتهن.
If we can change the way
لو إستطعنا تغيير طريقة
households believe and think,
تفكير و معتقدات الأسر،
we can change the way communities believe and think.
يمكننا أن نغير معتقدات و طرق تفكير المجتمعات.
And if we can change enough communities,
و لو إستطعنا تغيير ما يكفي من المجتمعات،
we can change national attitudes.
يمكننا تغيير مواقف قومية كاملة.
We can change national attitudes to women
نستطيع تغيير السلوك الوطني تجاه المرأة،
and national attitudes to HIV.
و السلوك الوطني تجاه الHIV.
The hardest barrier really is around stigma reduction.
أصعب الحواجز حقيقةً هو حاجز التغلب على جدار العار و الخزي.
We have the medicines, we have the tests,
لدينا العقاقير، و لدينا الإختبارات.
but how do you reduce the stigma?
و لكن كيف نتغلب على حاجز العار؟
And it's important about disclosure.
و من المهم الإفصاح عن الإصابة.
So, a couple years ago, one of the mentor mothers came back,
إذاً، منذ بضعة أعوام، عادت إحدى الأمهات المرشدات ،
and she told me a story.
و أطلعتني على قصة.
She had been asked by one of the clients
إحدى المريضات كانت قد طلبت منها
to go to the home of the client,
أن تتوجه معها إلى منزلها،
because the client wanted to tell the mother and her brothers and sisters
لأن المريضة أرادت أن تُخبر امها و إخوانها و أخواتها
about her HIV status,
عن إصابتها بالHIV.
and she was afraid to go by herself.
و كانت تخاف من الذهاب وحدها.
And so the mentor mother went along with.
فذهبت الأم المرشدة معها.
And the patient walked into the house
و دخلت المريضة إلى المنزل
and said to her mother and siblings,
و قالت لأمها و إخوانها،
"I have something to tell you. I'm HIV-positive."
"لدي ما أخبركم به. أنا مصابة بالHIV."
And everybody was quiet.
و إلتزم الجميع الصمت.
And then her oldest brother stood up and said,
ثم وقف شقيقها الكبير وقال،
"I too have something to tell you.
"أنا أيضاً لدي ما أقوله.
I'm HIV-positive.
أنا أيضاً مصاب بالHIV.
I've been afraid to tell everybody."
و كنت خائفا من إخبار الجميع."
And then this older sister stood up and said,
ثم وقفت شقيقتها الكبرى و قالت،
"I too am living with the virus,
"أنا أيضاً أحمل الفيروس،
and I've been ashamed."
و كنت أشعر بالخزي."
And then her younger brother stood up and said,
ثم وقف أخوها الصغير و قال،
"I'm also positive.
"أنا أيضاً مصاب.
I thought you were going to throw me out of the family."
إعتقدت أنكم ستطردوني من العائلة ."
And you see where this is going.
و تستطيعون رؤية إتجاه الحديث.
The last sister stood up and said, "I'm also positive.
وقفت آخر الشقيقات قائلة،" أنا أيضاً مصابة.
I thought you were going to hate me."
و إعتقدت أنكم ستكرهونني."
And there they were, all of them together for the first time
و ها هم جميعاً لأول مرة
being able to share this experience for the first time
قادرون على مشاركة خبراتهم للمرة الأولى،
and to support each other for the first time.
و على مساندة بعضهم البعض لأول مرة.
(Video) Female Narrator: Women come to us,
(فيديو) راوية : تَقصِدنا السيدات
and they are crying and scared.
وهن خائفات يبكين.
I tell them my story,
فأخبرهم قصتي،
that I am HIV-positive,
و أنني مصابة بالHIV،
but my child is HIV-negative.
و لكن طفلي ليس مصاب.
I tell them, "You are going to make it,
أخبرهم،" ستتمكنون من الصمود،
and you will raise a healthy baby."
و ستقوم بتنشأة طفل سليم."
I am proof that there is hope.
أنا دليل على أن هناك أملاً."
Mitchell Besser: Remember the images I showed you
ميتشيل بيسر: أتذكرون الصورة التي أريتكم
of how few doctors and nurses there are in Africa.
التي تظهر مدى قلة عدد الأطباء و الممرضات في إفريقيا.
And it is a crisis in health care systems.
و كيف أنها أزمة في أنظمة الرعاية الصحية.
Even as we have more tests and more drugs,
حتى و قد توفرت لدينا المزيد من الأدوية و الإختبارات،
we can't reach people; we don't have enough providers.
لا نستطيع الوصول إلى الناس، ليس لدينا ما يكفي من موفري الرعاية.
So we talk in terms of what we call task-shifting.
إذاً فنحن نحاول أن نتَّبع ما ندعوه بإنتقال المهام.
Task-shifting is traditionally
إنتقال المهام هو عامةً
when you take health care services from one provider
أن تنتقل خدمات الرعاية الصحية من راعٍ
and have another provider do it.
إلى آخر لتوفيرها.
Typically, it's a doctor giving a job to a nurse.
مثلاً كطبيب يكلف ممرضة بمهمة ما.
And the issue in Africa
و المشكلة في إفريقيا
is that there are fewer nurses, really than doctors,
أن عدد الممرضات أقل فعلاً من عدد الأطباء،
and so we need to find new paradigm for health care.
و لذا يجب علينا أن نجد نموذجاً جديداً للرعاية الصحية.
How do you build a better health care system?
كيف يمكنك بناء نظام رعاية صحية أفضل؟
We've chosen to redefine the health care system
إخترنا أن نعيد تعريف نظام الرعاية الصحية
as a doctor, a nurse and a mentor mother.
إلى طبيب، ممرضة، و أم مرشدة.
And so what nurses do
إذاً فما تقوم به الممرضة
is that they ask the mentor mothers to explain
هو أن تطلب من الأم المرشدة شرح
how to take the drugs, the side effects.
كيفية تناول الأدوية، و أعراضها الجانبية.
They delegate education about infant feeding,
يفوضوهن لتعليم النساء عن تغذية الرضّع،
family planning, safer sex,
تخطيط الأسرة، الجماع الآمن،
actions that nurses simple just don't have time for.
كل ما لا تجد الممرضة الوقت الكافي لشرحه.
So we go back to the prevention of mother to child transmission.
إذاً لنعد إلى الوقاية من إنتقال العدوى من الأم إلى الطفل.
The world is increasingly seeing these programs
العالم الآن نظر بشكل متزايد إلى تلك البرامج
as the bridge to comprehensive maternal and child health.
كجسر إلى الرعاية الصحية الشاملة للأم و الطفل.
And our organization
و منظمتنا
helps women across that bridge.
تساعد النساء على عبور هذا الجسر.
The care doesn't stop when the baby's born --
و الرعاية لا تتوقف بعد ولادة الطفل.
we deal with the ongoing health of the mother and baby,
نحن نستمر في رعاية صحة الأم و الطفل
ensuring that they live healthy,
لنتأكد من أنهم يعيشون حياة صحيّة،
successful lives.
و ناجحة.
Our organization works on three levels.
تعمل منظمتنا على ثلاث مستويات.
The first, at the patient level --
الأول، مستوى المريض --
mothers and babies keeping babies from getting HIV,
الأمهات و الأطفال للوقاية من إصابة الطفل بالHIV،
keeping mothers healthy to raise them.
و الإبقاء على صحة الأم لترعاه.
The second, communities --
الثاني - المجتمعات --
empowering women.
و تقوية المرأة.
They become leaders within their communities.
إنهن يصبحن قائدات في مجتمعاتهن.
They change the way communities think --
ليغيروا طريقة تفكير المجتمعات.
we need to change attitudes to HIV.
نحن بحاجة لتغيير السلوك تجاه الHIV.
We need to change attitudes to women in Africa.
نحن في حاجة إلى تغيير السلوك تجاه النساء في افريقيا.
We have to do that.
يجب أن نفعل ذلك.
And then rework the level of the health care systems,
ثم نعيد صياغة المستوى الثالث، أنظمة الرعاية الصحية،
building stronger health care systems.
لنبني أنظمة رعاية قوية.
Our health care systems are broken.
أنظمة الرعاية الصحية لدينا ضعيفة.
They're not going to work the way they're currently designed.
و لن تُفلح في مهمتها بالشكل الذي هي عليه الآن.
And so doctors and nurses
و بالتالي الأطباء و الممرضات
who need to try to change people's behaviors
المطلوب منهم تغيير سلوكيات الناس
don't have the skills, don't have the time --
ليست لديهم المهارات و لا الوقت الكافيين.
our mentor mothers do.
أما أمهاتنا المرشدات فلديهن كلاهما.
And so in redefining the health care teams by bringing the mentor mothers in,
إذاً بإعادة تعريف فرق الرعاية الصحية بدمج الأمهات المرشدات فيها،
we can do that.
يمكننا أن ننجح.
I started the program in Capetown, South Africa
لقد بدأت هذا البرنامج في كيب تاون بجنوب إفريقيا
back in 2001.
في 2001.
It was at that point, just the spark of an idea.
كان حينها مجرد شرارة لفكرة.
Referencing Steven Johnson's very lovely speech yesterday
وبالإشارة إلى حديث ستيفن جونسون الرائع بالأمس
on where ideas come from,
عن من أين تأتي الأفكار،
I was in the shower at the time --
فقد كنت أستحم حين جائتني الفكرة.
I was alone.
كنت بمفردي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The program is now working in nine countries,
و الآن البرنامج مفعَّل في تسع دول.
we have 670 program sites,
لدينا 670 موقع عمل للبرنامج.
we're seeing about 230,000
و نتابع حوالي 230.000
women every month,
إمرأة شهرياً.
we're employing 1,600 mentor mothers,
تعمل لدينا 1.600 أم مرشدة.
and last year, they enrolled
و في العام الماضي،قد أشركوا
300,000 HIV-positive pregnant women and mothers.
300.000 إمرأة حامل و أم مصابة بالHIV.
That is 20 percent
و هذا 20 بالمائة
of the global HIV-positive pregnant women --
من مجموع الحوامل المصابات بالمرض عالمياً.
20 percent of the world.
20 بالمائة من نسبة العالم.
What's extraordinary is how simple the premise is.
و الغريب هو مدى بساطة الفكرة الأساسية.
Mothers with HIV caring for mothers with HIV.
الأمهات المصابات بالHIV يعتنين بمثيلتهن.
Past patients taking care of present patients.
المرضى السابقين يعتنين بالمرضى الحاليين.
And empowerment through employment --
و التحفيز من خلال التوظيف.
reducing stigma.
محو وصمة العار.
(Video) Female Narrator: There is hope,
(فيديو) الراوية: هذا هو الأمل،
hope that one day
الأمل أنه يوماً ما
we shall win this fight
سنربح المعركة
against HIV and AIDS.
ضد الإيدز و الHIV.
Each person must know
يجب أن يكون الجميع على دراية
their HIV status.
بحالتهم نسبةً للHIV.
Those who are HIV-negative
فمن هم غير مصابين بالمرض
must know how to stay negative.
يجب أن يعرفوا كيف يظلوا كذلك.
Those who are HIV-infected
و من هم مصابين بالمرض
must know how
يجب أن يعرفوا كيف
to take care of themselves.
يعتنوا بأنفسهم.
HIV-positive pregnant women
يجب أن تحصل السيدات الحوامل
must get PMTCT services
المصابات بالHIV على خدمات PMTCT
in order to have
من أجل أن ينجبن
HIV-negative babies.
أطفالاً أصحاء.
All of this is possible,
و كل هذا ممكن،
if we each contribute to this fight.
إذا إشتركنا جميعاً في تلك المعركة.
MB: Simple solutions to complex problems.
م.ب.: حلول بسيطة لمشكلات معقدة.
Mothers caring for mothers.
أمهات يعتنين بأمهات.
It's transformational.
إنها نقطة تحول.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)